Guide to the Ireland House Oral History Collection AIA.030
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- O
  - O'Leary, Stella, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Stella O'Leary (b. Dublin, Ireland, 1938) won a UNESCO scholarship to travel to America to archive a collection of rare Irish books and manuscripts at the Catholic University of America. In 1996 she founded Irish American Democrats, an organization whose goal was to ensure continuation of the Irish peace process.
  - O'Mahony, Donal, Oct 5, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    Donal O'Mahony (b. Clonakilty, Co. Cork, Ireland, 1968) studied ceramics, worked as a painter/decorator in Boston, and as a barman at the Brendan Behan pub. He is facilities manager at Canton High School.
  - O'Mahony, Rosaleen, Oct 5, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    Rosaleen O'Mahony (b. New York, New York, 1967) studied ceramics before emigrating to Boston in 1989 where she re-trained as a nurse who specializes in elder care.
  - O'Neill, John, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    John O'Neill (b. Labasheeda, Co. Clare, 1930) came to United States in 1949 and within two years joined the County Clare Association of New York. He worked for the MTA for 39 years and at weekends played music in the John O'Neill Band. He raised 4 children on Long Island.
  - O'Rourke, Hugh, Jan 14, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Hugh O’Rourke was born in the Bronx, New York in 1942. He was the son of immigrants from Tyrone and Kerry, Ireland, who arrived in the 1910s and 1920s. Hugh is now retired from the NYPD and has a Ph.D. from the City University of New York. Hugh is the father of Mary O’Rourke who is also a contributor to this collection of oral histories.
    Some of the themes discussed in this interview include: Irishness and the police force; growing up in the Bronx in the 1940s; Irish New Yorkers and some degree of apathy towards further education; his father and being a Democrat; his parents' view of Ireland versus Hugh’s view of Ireland (more positive); and the Irish enclave in East Durham, New York.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview is approximately 160 minutes long, on 3 CDs. The interview took place in New York City on January 14, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - O'Rourke, Kevin, Jun 10, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    Kevin O'Rourke (b. Bern, Switzerland, 1963) studied for a Ph.D. in economics at Harvard University before returning to Ireland in 1994 to teach at University College Dublin, Trinity College Dublin, and, as Chichele Professor of Economic History, University of Oxford.
  - O'Rourke, Mary, Apr 17, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Mary O’Rourke was born on Long Island, New York, in 1980. A teacher by profession, she is an avid soccer and gaelic football player. She is third generation Irish and has a lot of interaction with young Irish immigrants, due to her involvement in Irish sports. Mary is the daughter of Hugh O’Rourke, who is also a contributor to this collection of oral histories.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 1 hour long, on 1 CD. The interview took place in New York City on April 17, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - O'Rourke, Sheila, Jun 1, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Sheila O’Rourke was born in San Francisco in 1939, the daughter of Kerry immigrants who arrived in the 1910s and 1920s. She has worked in financial and customer service environments for most of her career.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 2 hours, 43 minutes long, on 3 CDs. The interview took place in San Francisco, California, on June 1, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - O'Sullivan, Kathleen and Downing, Albine, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - O'Sullivan, Sheena, Feb 13, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Sheena O’Sullivan was born in London, to Irish immigrants, in 1969. At the age of six months, her family returned to Cahirciveen, Co. Kerry, Ireland. Sheena immigrated to New York in 1994 and has since trained as a nurse. She is married to another Irish immigrant and is the sister of Catriona Hayes, who is also a contributor to this collection of oral histories.
    Some of the key themes in this interview are: her parents' break-up in 1970s Ireland and lack of overt class differences; the significance of returning to higher education in the US; why London didn’t ever appeal to her; Irish nurses in the US and how they are seen in comparison with Ireland; the American Dream (track 5); and the Celtic Tiger.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 48 minutes long, on 1 CD. The interview took place in Middle Village, New York, on February 13, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
- P
  - Petters, Mary and Hale, Marie, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Phelan, Patricia, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Patricia Phelan (b. Flatbush, New York, 1949) traces her Irish roots to an 1800 immigrant arrival on her mother's side and to the 1830s on her father's. She is a descendent of David Samuel Stewart who was the alderman for the 7th ward in Brooklyn in the closing decades of the nineteenth century. Raised in Garden City on Long Island, she married the novelist Tom Phelan.
  - Prendiville, Sean, May 31, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Sean Prendiville Papers (AIA 005)
    Sean Prendiville was born in San Francisco in 1951, the son of Irish immigrants from Kerry and Roscommon. He attended Catholic high school at St. Ignatius, in the Haight-Ashbury district, and graduated from the University of San Francisco in 1973. Sean worked at the Plough and the Stars, an Irish bar in San Francisco, where he met his wife Eileen, before establishing a career in the computer business.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 2 hours and 20 minutes long, on 3 CDs. The interview took place in San Francisco on May 31, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
- Q
  - Quigley, Martin, May 21, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Martin Quigley was born in Chicago in 1917. He graduated from Georgetown University in 1939 and worked as a journalist in the film industry. In the 1940s, Martin worked as an undercover agent for the U.S. Office of Secret Services gathering intelligence in Ireland on the issue of neutrality during World War II. He went on to receive a Ph.D. at Columbia University and led a career in writing, politics and education. Martin is the author of several books, including A US Spy in Ireland and Great Gaels: Ireland and Peace in a World at War.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 130 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place in West Hartford, Connecticut, on May 21, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Quinlan, Tom, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Tom Quinlan (b. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1925), the grandson of immigrants from Counties Cork and Fermanagh, taught English for many years.
  - Quinn, Charles B., Jun 10, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Quinn, Florence, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Florence Quinn (b. Bristol, Connecticut, 1955) is the President and founder of Quinn & Co., a public relations firm in Manhattan.
  - Quinn, Marion, Sep 30, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    Marion Quinn (b. Chicago, Illinois, 1964) is the youngest child and only daughter in a family of five children. Her parents, Michael and Teresa Quinn met through family connections. Both were born and raised in County Offaly Ireland. They married in 1956. Her parents migrated from Ireland to Canada, then to London, England before settling in Chicago where her father, an English literature professor, taught at Loyola University.
  - Quinn, Peter, Nov 11, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Peter Quinn (b. 1947) is a writer and self-proclaimed BIC – Bronx Irish Catholic – whose roots date back to the famine generation. Peter began his career as a speech writer for New York State Governors Mario Cuomo and Hugh Carey, both Democrats, before moving on to become editorial director for Time, Inc. His first novel, The Banished Children of Eve, is set during the Draft Riots of 1863. Retired from the corporate world, Peter’s latest novel is The Man Who Never Returned about the infamous disappearance of New York State Supreme Court Judge Force Crater in the 1930s.
  - Quinn, Sean, Feb 7, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Sean Quinn was born in New York in 1947, the son of Irish immigrants from Monaghan and Armagh. Sean inherited a talent for music from his father, Irish fiddler Louis Quinn, and as a child in the 1950s Sean learned to play with Irish musicians who gathered in his family’s home in Queens. One of seven children, Sean and his siblings formed the musical group the Quinn Family, which recorded and toured Ireland. He is a musician and music teacher in New York.
    Some of the key themes discussed in this interview are: JFK’s death; the significance of music as a way of uniting people; influences of Riverdance and the Clancys and Tommy Makem; and growing up as the son of a well-known musician.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 2 hours long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place on February 7, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Quinn, Terry, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    Terry Quinn (b. Brooklyn, New York) a veteran of the New York Fire Department and the father of three children, has roots in County Roscommon. He has spent many years in the bar business in New York City and was a technical adviser to the television show Rescue Me.
- R
  - Reidy, Sr. Virgilius, Apr 8, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    Sister Virgilius Reidy was born in 1913 in Ballymacelligott, Co. Kerry, Ireland, the youngest of ten children. She lost her brother Jack when he was killed by the Black and Tans in 1920. Sister Virgilius entered the order of Franciscan Sisters in 1931 and immigrated to America in 1934. She began teaching and served as Mother Superior in schools in the East New York section of Brooklyn. In the 1950s she worked in Augusta and Savannah, Georgia, where she witnessed racial integration in public schools, and taught future Supreme Court Justice Clarence Thomas.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 40 minutes long. The interview took place in Tenafly, New Jersey, on April 8, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Reilly, Fr. Gavin, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
    Fr. Gavin Reilly of the Capuchin Order (b. Brooklyn, New York, 1928) graduated from the Pontifical Gregorian University, Rome in 1958. Fr. Reilly has taught theology at the Capuchin Theological Seminary in Garrison, New York and at St. Anselm's College in Manchester, New Hampshire.
  - Reilly, Megan, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Megan Reilly (b. Memphis, Tennessee, 1976) is a singer and songwriter who has been called one of the "Top Nine Emerging Songwriters".
  - Ridge, John, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
    John T. Ridge (b. Brooklyn, New York, 1947), the son of immigrants from Galway and Longford, is an historian who has documented the history of the Ancient Order of Hibernians and the St. Patrick's Day Parade as well as many other aspects of New York Irish history. In 2011 he published Celebrating 250 Years of the New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade. He has been a long-time officer, including President, of the New York Irish History Roundtable.
    John T. Ridge Collection (AIA 068)
  - Rodriguez, Margaret, Nov 12, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    Margaret Rodriguez (b. New York, New York, 1938) is the daughter of Irish immigrant parents from Counties Roscommon and Cork. She began working for NYU in 1969 and stayed until her retirement in 2011.
  - Rogers, James, Oct 9. 2009 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    James Silas Rogers was born in 1952 in St. Paul, MN. He traces Irish ancestry through his mother’s family, the Davitts, who immigrated from Mayo in the 19th Century. James became involved with the Irish American Cultural Institute in 1983 and initiated a degree program in Irish Studies at Metropolitan State University, in St. Paul, MN. He is the editor of the New Hibernia Review, managing director of the Center for Irish Studies at the University of St. Thomas, and president of the American Conference for Irish Studies.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview is approximately 2 hours, 18 minutes long. The interview took place in New York City on October 9, 2009, and the interviewer was Marion Casey.
  - Rohs, Steve, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
    Steve Rohs (b. Cincinnati, Ohio, 1965) is a professor of American Studies at Michigan State University's James Madison College of Public Affairs. He is the author of Eccentric Nation: Irish Embodiment and Performance in Nineteenth Century New York City (2009). Raised in a West Side working class Catholic family, he is of German ancestry on his father's side. His mother is descended from Brian (Barnard) White who emigrated from Sligo to avoid jail in 1852 and worked as a stonemason in Cincinnati.
  - Rooney, James E., Nov 9, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    Rooney discussed the significant role that family and tradition plays in his life. He also discussed his ties to Mayo and Newry, Co. Down, Ireland. His great grandfather, Dan Rooney, and great grandmother Margaret Devlan, emigrated from Ireland to Wales via Prince Edward Island for 10 years, and then came to Coulter, Pa (outside of Pittsburgh) in the United States.
    When the Rooney’s arrived in America, Jim’s great grandfather, Dan Rooney, a distinct leader in the 1st Ward of Pittsburgh’s North Side, opened a bar on Federal Street. The bar encapsulates the Rooney’s future business style in that it led to his grandfather’s introduction into professional boxing and sports as well as leading him into the position of 1st Ward Chairman on the North Side, which evolved his career into politics.
    His grandfather, Art “The Chief” Rooney, was married to Kathleen McNulty in June of 1931 and had 5 children. He grew up and lived all his life in the North Side of Pittsburgh. He was an adamant sports fan and loved to gamble. He played minor league baseball from 1920-1925, and made the Olympic Boxing Team in 1920, but did not participate. He also played in many minor league football teams around Pittsburgh. Jim referred several times to his grandfather as a risk taker.
    His maternal grandparents came to America from Ballaghaderreen, County Mayo, Ireland. Martin Reagan came in 1921 and sent for his wife Mary Duffy in 1923.2 of 10 kids grew up in Pittsburgh’s North Side, which he refers to as the Irish Ghetto in the turn of the 19th century. Rooney grew up there, too. His mom went to University of Pittsburgh later in life to gain the education that she had always wanted. His mom viewed vernaculars as an anathema, and had a ‘tough as nails’ personality that he asserts to the large family that she was in care of. His maternal grandmother is still alive today at the age of 96. Jim notes that his mother and grandmother are very similar in their tough personalities. He talked about the role his mother, Patricia Reagan, and his grandmother, Mary Duffy, played in his childhood. They emphasized education and compassion, while maintaining a ‘tough as nails’ demeanor. However he talks about his dad being the biggest influence in his adult life. He says this is because his dads inability to engage with a child. He discussed that his mother and father had met in the first grade and grew up together.
    Dan Rooney, Jim Rooney’s father, was born 7-30-1932 on the North Side of Pittsburgh, PA and is the current owner of the Pittsburgh Steelers football team, which was passed down to him from his father Art “The Chief” Rooney in 1975. He was a member of the 1950 class at North Catholic High School and the 1955 class at Duquesne University. He is the Vice-Chairman of the American Ireland Fund, involved in The United Way of America, The American Diabetes Association, Presbyterian University Hospital, The Pittsburgh History and Landmarks Foundation and Duquesne University. He is also the benefactor of the Rooney Prize for Irish Literature, the founder of the Newry-Pittsburgh Partnership, and is the 3rd person to ever receive the Charter of Newry. He was also inducted into the Pro Football Hall of Fame in 2000.
    He talks of his St. Bernard’s and Gilmour Academy Catholic School upbringing in St. Peter’s parish on the North Side of Pittsburgh, PA. Jim tells how his own kids have continued on, with the tradition of Catholic Schooling. He discusses the unique blend that Catholic school brings to a child’s education. He also talks of his ties to St. Peters Church near the Steelers stadium on the North Side of Pittsburgh and how everyone in his family has been baptized and married there and that he still goes to church there.
    After his completion of college, he went to South Africa and worked with diabetic youth, which he says opened his eyes up to working with Ireland. In the mid 90’s, right after he got out of college, he went to Belfast to support his father’s efforts with the Ireland Fund. He was inspired by the immense economic growth that he witnessed from the first visit to Ireland in 1976 to his current visits in the 90’s, which motivated him to remain involved with efforts in Ireland.
    A year after completing Boston College, Jim traveled to South America to work with diabetic youth. After this, in the mid-90’s Jim’s father, Dan Rooney, asked him to take up business dealings in Belfast to support his father’s work with the American Ireland Fund.
    In 2001, he ran for state Senate as Democrat and lost, but has worked for many political campaigns. His wife steered him away from politics due to the stress and exposure in politics.
    He talks about his five attempts at starting his own business, in which two have failed, one has been slightly successful and his current engagement is in progress. Part of his current business involved him in the creation of security robots called the ‘Kuchera Robots’ for the 2006 Super Bowl in Detroit as the director of First Link. The Kuchera Robot is a 30-pound robot that spins, crawls and looks through windows by remote control and takes photos; created for the use in Iraq, but used in the 2006 Super Bowl. First Link is in charge of marketing ideas, and works with Pantherlab Works to advance the technology in the ideas.
    Jim Rooney was interviewed at New York University’s Glucksman Ireland House on November 9th 2006 by Amanda Snatchko and Marion Casey. The interview took place before Jim was scheduled to talk about his father and the Steelers tradition later that night at the Glucksman Ireland House as well.
    James E. Rooney (b. Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1967), director of FirstLink at the University of Pittsburgh's Institute for Entrepreneurial Excellence, Katz Graduate School of Business, and grandson of Pittsburgh Steelers founder Art Rooney.
  - Ryan, Fr. Gerald R., Nov 17, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    Ryan discusses the neighborhood in which he grew up. He describes 1920’s Pelham Bay in the Bronx as farmland with fruit trees and gardens. He remembers his childhood as well as his family, specifically his mother and father, immigrants from Ireland who met in New York City. He discusses his Catholic upbringing and describes his parents’ reaction to his desire to be a priest; his mother’s delight and his father’s support.
    After attending P.S. 71 for three years, Ryan attended the parish elementary school of Our Lady of Assumption after it opened in 1928, graduating in 1933. He continued his education at Cathedral College for high school and his first two years of college and then St. Joseph’s Seminary for the remainder of his college education and seminary training. He reveals his father’s belief that he should always pay his own way and because of his conviction, he would not allow Ryan to attend Seminary school on credit as the rest of the seminarians did.
    On January 27, 1945 Gerald Ryan was ordained by Cardinal Francis Spellman (1889–1967). Twelve years after entering the seminary in a class of ninety-nine, sixteen were ordained. He discusses the changes in the Catholic Church and the seminary since his pre-Vatican II educational training, including the drop in numbers of young men with vocations.
    While waiting for a position as an English teacher at Cardinal Hayes High School, Ryan was assigned to St. Anthony of Padua parish in the Bronx immediately after ordination. He discusses his adjustments to parish life in an African-American community and how he came interested in the civil rights movement. Ryan marched in Washington, DC and heard the famous “I Have a Dream” speech given by Dr. Martin Luther King in 1963, and two years later joined King and other religious leaders in Selma, Alabama to cross the Edmund Pettus Bridge in support of African-American voting rights. He describes the bus ride to Selma and the unknown fear of what could happen during the march. He tells the story of the angry southerners yelling at those participating in the protest and how the atmosphere changed once the crowd recognized singer Harry Belafonte in the line of marchers. Back in New York, Ryan continued to participate in demonstrations on issues affecting all poor communities such as housing and health.
    Ryan served at St. Anthony’s until he was assigned as pastor of St. Luke’s parish in 1966. Several years later he learned that the call for a teaching position never came in 1945 because the pastor of St. Anthony’s had personally requested of the Cardinal that Ryan remain in the parish to work with him. Looking back, Ryan feels that remaining at St. Anthony’s instead of leaving to teach was for the best.
    As pastor of St. Luke’s parish, Ryan ministers to a primarily Hispanic community. He discusses the differences in participation between his current parish and the primarily Irish parish he belonged to as a child. He tells of the current parishioners’ interest in participating in the liturgy and running of the parish. He speaks of the irony that as a young priest he served with three other priests in a parish and now as an older man he is the only priest in a bi-lingual parish. Ryan is currently the longest serving pastor in the diocese of New York. He spends his day running the parish with his other staff and administering to his parishioners’ needs. In addition to saying the majority of the masses at St. Luke’s, he works with the parish council and leads a weekly session for the troubled teens of the parish.
    Ryan concludes the interview by discussing his opinions on the reasons for the lack of vocations to the priesthood and the loss of American Catholic faith. He speaks of his love for Ireland and in particular his special devotion to the Shrine of Our Lady of Knock in County Mayo.
    Rev. Msgr. Gerald Ryan was interviewed at New York University’s Glucksman Ireland House on 17 November 2005 by Natalie Rose and Linda Dowling Almeida. This oral history with Msgr. Gerald Ryan was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview is 99 minutes long, on two CDs and had been logged at ten-minute intervals.
    Fr. Gerald R. Ryan (b. New York, New York, 1920), pastor of St. Luke's R.C. Church in the South Bronx and the longest serving pastor in the Archdiocese of New York.
  - Rygor, Stanley and Kathleen, May 14, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 58)